Benjamin Gerig Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Benjamin Gerig Papers 1927-1974 1930-1968
MSS61974
Gerig, Benjamin, 1894-1976
2,000 items
6 containers plus 2 classified
2.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Diplomat. Correspondence, reports, memoranda, printed material, and other papers pertaining to Gerig's service with the League of Nations primarily as commissioner-general of the pavilion at the New York World's Fair in 1939 and 1940, his work with the Department of State in a number of positions involving international organizations and the administration of trust territories, and his membership on the United Nations Trusteeship Council.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950--Correspondence.; Bunche, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson), 1904-1971--Correspondence.; Cordier, Andrew W. (Andrew Wellington), 1901-1975--Correspondence.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959--Correspondence.; Erp, J. W. T. van--Correspondence.; Field, Noel Haviland, 1904-1970--Correspondence.; Gerig, Benjamin, 1894-1976.; Gerig, Mary, 1898-1960--Correspondence.; Gerig, Pearl--Correspondence.; Hiss, Alger--Correspondence.; Jessup, Philip C. (Philip Caryl), 1897-1986--Correspondence.; Lester, Sean, 1888-1959--Correspondence.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, Jr., 1902-1985--Correspondence.; Manship, Paul, 1885-1966--Correspondence.; Morley, Felix M. (Felix Muskett), 1894-1982--Correspondence.; Pickard, Bertram, 1892-1973--Correspondence.; Sweetser, Arthur, 1888-1968--Correspondence.; Sweetser, Ruth Gregory--Correspondence.; Tomlinson, John D. (John Doren), 1903-1981--Correspondence.; Walters, F. P. (Francis Paul), 1888- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Conversations on International Organization (1944: Washington, D.C.); League of Nations.; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.); Preparatory Commission of the United Nations.; United Nations Conference on International Organization (1945: San Francisco, Calif.); United Nations Visiting Mission to Trust Territories in West Africa.; United Nations.; United Nations. Trusteeship Council.; United States. Department of State.
Subjects
Colonies--Africa.; Colonies.; International agencies.; International organization.; International trusteeships--Africa, West.; International trusteeships.; Mandates.; Nuclear weapons--Testing.; Race relations.
Places
Soviet Union--Colonies.
Occupations
Diplomats.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Orie Benjamin Gerig, diplomat, were given to the Library of Congress in 1986 by his son, John Gerig.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Library’s Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Benjamin Gerig are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1894, Jan. 18 Born, Smithville, Ohio
1917 B.A., Goshen College, Goshen, Ind.
1921 1923 Instructor of political economy, University of Illinois, Chicago, Ill.
1922 A.M., University of Illinois, Chicago, Ill. Married Mary Blosser (died 1960)
1923 1928 Professor of economics, Simmons College, Boston, Mass.
1928 1929 Fellow, Post-graduate Institute of International Studies, Geneva, Switzerland D.Sc., political science, Université de Genève, Geneva, Switzerland
1930 Published The Open Door and the Mandates System. London: G. Allen & Unwin Ltd.
1930 1939 Member, Information and Mandates Section, League of Nations Secretariat
1939 1940 Commissioner-General, League of Nations Pavilion, New York World's Fair, New York, N.Y.
1940 1942 Associate professor of government, Haverford College, Haverford, Pa.
1942 Lecturer, political science, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa. Divisional assistant, Division of Special Research, State Department
1944 Technical advisor, United States delegation, Dumbarton Oaks Conference, Washington, D.C.
1944 1961 Chief, Division of Dependent Area Affairs, State Department
1945 Adviser, United States delegation, United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, Calif. Principal advisor to United States representative and alternate delegate, Executive Committee, Preparatory Commission of the United Nations, London, England
1945 1961 Chief, Division of Department Area Affairs; associate chief, Division of International Organization Affairs, State Department\
1946 Adviser, United States delegation, United Nations General Assembly, first session
1947 1953 Chairman, Interdepartmental Committee of United States Government on Non-self-governing Territories
1948 United States representative, United Nations Special Committee on Information from Non-self-governing Territories, Geneva, Switzerland; adviser, United States delegation, United Nations General Assembly, Paris, France
1960 Superior Service Award for service as director, Office of Dependent Area Affairs, State Department
1961 Retired, State Department Honorary doctor of laws, Haverford College, Haverford, Pa.
1963 Married Pearl Van Pelt Harris
1966 Coauthor, International Peace Observation, a History and Forecast. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins Press
1976, Feb. 26 Died, Venice, Fla.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Benjamin Orig Gerig (1894-1976) span the years 1927-1974, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1930-1968. The collection contains correspondence, reports, memoranda, printed matter, and other material documenting Gerig's service with the League of Nations, 1930-1940; the Department of State in a number of positions relating to international organizations and the administration of the trust territories, 1942-1961; and with the Trusteeship Council of the United Nations, 1947-1953. Gerig was deeply involved in preparations for the formation of the United Nations and served as an advisor to United States delegations to conferences at Dumbarton Oaks and San Francisco, 1944-1945, the Preparatory Commission of the United Nations in London, and the first session of the General Assembly in 1946. The Gerig Papers are arranged by general correspondence, speeches and writings, subject files, and classified material.
General correspondence, 1930-1974, contains personal and professional correspondence between Gerig and friends, family, and associates, predominantly those connected with the League of Nations and the State Department. Correspondents include Isaiah Bowman, Ralph J. Bunche, Andrew W. Cordier, John Foster Dulles, J. W. T. van Erp, Noel Haviland Field, Philip C. Jessup, Sean Lester, Henry Cabot Lodge, P. W. Martin, Felix M. Morley, Bertram Pickard, John D. Tomlinson, and F. P. Walters. Letters of appreciation and recommendation for Gerig were written by Warren R. Austin, Archibald MacLeish, Mike Mansfield, Leo Pasvolsky, Dean Rusk, Edward R. Stettinius, and Adlai E. Stevenson. Additional correspondence, particularly with League officials, is found in the subject file. Letters that Gerig wrote on the versos of committee reports commenting on his work on the Preparatory Commission of the United Nations in London are located in the subject file with other Preparatory Commission material.
The largest group of general correspondence is between Gerig and his first wife Mary and second wife Pearl and longtime friend and colleague Arthur Sweetser and his wife Ruth Gregory Sweetser, with whom the Gerigs shared a summer home in Kitty Hawk, North Carolina. A letter from Gerig to Sweetser, dated from Geneva, January 1, 1950, comments on the Alger Hiss conviction and John Foster Dulles's testimony. Much of the correspondence was written after Gerig's retirement from the State Department in 1961. Arrangement of the general correspondence is alphabetical by name and chronological therein.
Among the speeches and writings, 1930-1969, are drafts and notes as well as published speeches and articles. The speeches include remarks given on League of Nations Day, 1939; an address on dependent peoples delivered as deputy United States representative on the United Nations Trusteeship Council, 1948; an address on the role of the United Nations in African developments, 1960; and outlines of remarks on the colonial question and the United Nations, international organizations, and sovereignty. Writings include publications by the Geneva Research Information Committee in Geneva Special Studies, 1930-1931; a statement on progress in the French Cameroons in the State Department Bulletin, 1956; and typescripts on the United States and the colonial question, 1955-1956. Arrangement is alphabetical by type of material and chronological therein.
The subject file, 1927-1969, consists of correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, reports, press releases, and printed matter dealing with Gerig's activities with the League of Nations, his work in planning for a new international organization and transferring to it League of Nations assets, and dependent area affairs and colonial policy, especially as it related to African nations, in the State Department and the United Nations Trusteeship Council. Arrangement is alphabetical by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material, and chronological therein.
Much of the material in the subject file, especially that on the origins of the United Nations, is security classified. Material in the classified portion has been arranged according to the organization of the unclassified Gerig Papers. Notices in the unclassified portion alert researchers that sensitive matter has been removed. Folder titles given in the container list for the classified segment duplicate the pertinent folder titles from the unclassified portion.
Material documenting Gerig's tenure with the League of Nations is almost exclusively connected with his assignment as commissioner-general of the pavilion at the New York World's Fair in 1939 and 1940; correspondence with League officials predominantly concerns pavilion business and arrangements for Gerig's move from Geneva to New York. The files contain documents concerning building arrangements and contracts, insurance and shipping, and correspondence regarding exhibits, including correspondence with Paul Manship concerning his sculpture for the pavilion and damage suffered during its display.
Gerig was employed by the State Department in 1943 as an expert on trusteeship and colonial questions and served as advisor to United States delegations to Dumbarton Oaks and San Francisco conferences. In 1943, he chaired a group that wrote an early draft charter for the United Nations. Numerous early drafts are found in the State Department portion of the subject file. Files of the Office of Special Political Affairs include proposals regarding a new court of international justice, considerations regarding the location of the international organization, and papers prepared and initialed by State Department consultant Quincy Wright on the legal foundations of the postwar order, representation and voting, international policing and military sanctions, and trust territories.
In 1943, Gerig served as advisor to the United States delegation to the Dumbarton Oaks conference of four "great powers;" the full United Nations Conference on International Organization at San Francisco, April-June 1945; and the Preparatory Commission of the United Nations, London, England, September-November 1945. Much of the material in the files generated at these conferences concerns the transfer of the League of Nations and its assets to the United Nations. Correspondents include Alger Hiss, director of the Office of Special Political Affairs. Gerig prepared a memorandum at Senator Arthur Vandenberg's request explaining the points at which the Dumbarton Oaks proposals were an improvement over the League of Nations Covenant in terms of security, economic and social cooperation, and general organization. San Francisco Conference documents include comments and proposed amendments concerning the Dumbarton Oaks proposals submitted by national delegations to the conference, drafts and suggested changes to article five of the chapter relative to trusteeship, and reports.
Gerig served as deputy United States representative on the Trusteeship Council of the United Nations and travelled in Africa as chairman of the United Nations Visiting Mission to Trust Territories in West Africa in 1958. Files related to West Africa contain reports and correspondence relevant to the mission and letters and writings on West Africa, especially Cameroon. Gerig was offered an ambassadorship to West Cameroon which he declined because of his wife's failing health. He was also named to delegations celebrating the independence of both Cameroon and Togo. As chief of the Division of Dependent Area Affairs, his files contain memoranda and correspondence regarding colonial policy, foreign service dispatches, and reports, speeches, publications and clippings on dependent area affairs.
Material in the United Nations file includes working papers and press releases on the operations of the mandate system under the League of Nations, on non-self-governing territories, race relations and the territories, press releases of statements by Gerig on Ruanda-Urundi (present-day Rwanda and Burundi), Cameroon, and Togo, nuclear tests in trust territories, the growth of Soviet colonialism, and Trusteeship Council verbatim records pertaining to Ruanda-Urundi, trust territories, and General Assembly resolutions. Also included are draft articles on international trusteeship, telegrams, and memoranda regarding trusteeship questions.
The subject file also includes correspondence with Felix Morley and others at Haverford College and the University of Pennsylvania concerning academic appointments, 1942, and an honorary doctorate awarded by Haverford College in 1961; a pamphlet by Jacob B. Meyer on conscientious objectors in World War I, including Gerig; and State Department personnel records, such as letters of appointment, some signed by Presidents Truman and Eisenhower, travel orders, efficiency and performance ratings, certificates, press releases, and the superior service award Gerig received in 1960. Biographical material concerns the deaths of Arthur and Ruth Sweetser as well as correspondence and material gathered by Sweetser at the time of Gerig's heart attack and Mary Gerig's death in 1961.
Some photographs, including portraits of Gerig, have been retained in the subject file. Photographs of the League of Nations, 1931, of the League of Nations Pavilion, 1939, of Trusteeship Council representatives, 1960, and of the United Nations visiting mission to West Africa in 1949 have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged as general correspondence, speeches and writings, subject files, and classified material.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - Letters to family, 1942-1945 See also Container 4, Committee reports, annotated with letters home (Box 1)
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Bowman, Isaiah, 1944 (Box 1)
  - "B-L" miscellaneous, 1930, 1940-1971 (Box 1)
  - Morley, Felix, 1944 (Box 1)
  - "M" miscellaneous, 1940-1945, 1952-1962, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Pickard, Bertram, 1940 (Box 1)
  - "P-R" miscellaneous, 1943-1946, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Stettinius, Edward R., 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Sweetser, Arthur and Ruth, 1940, 1946-1950, 1956-1967, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - "S-W" miscellaneous, 1952, 1962, 1974 (Box 1)
- Speeches and writings (Box 1)
  - Speeches (Box 1)
    - "Address on League of Nations Day," New York, N.Y., 1939 (Box 1)
    - "The Colonial Question and the United Nations," undated (Box 1)
    - International organizations and sovereignty, Kew, London, circa 1963 (Box 1)
    - "The Role of the United Nations in African Developments," circa 1960 (Box 1)
    - "A Square Deal for Dependent Peoples," Newark, N.J., 1948 (Box 1)
    - United Nations and international relations, Sarasota, Fla., 1969 (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 1)
    - "Colonialism in the Modern World," undated (Box 1)
    - Geneva special studies, 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - "Progress in the French Cameroons," 1956 (Box 1)
    - "United States Attitude on the Colonial Question," 1955 (Box 1)
    - "United States Policy and the Colonial Question," 1956 (Box 1)
- Subject file (Box 1)
  - Academic appointments and awards (Box 1)
    - Haverford College, Haverford, Pa. (Box 1)
      - Honorary doctorate of laws, 1961 (Box 1)
      - Leave of absence for State Department work, 1942 (Box 1)
    - University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa., appointment as lecturer, Wharton School, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Conference on the United States and the United Nations, Washington, D.C., 1961 (Box 1)
  - Conscientious objectors in World War I, memoirs of Jacob B. Meyer mentioning Gerig's service, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Death of Mary Gerig and illness of Benjamin Gerig, correspondence and biographical tributes collected by Arthur Sweetser, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - Dumbarton Oaks Conference, Washington, D.C. (Box 2)
    - Conversations, minutes, and documents, 1944 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Notebook, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Formulation Group, 1944 (Box 2)
      - Drafts and proposals, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Memoranda and reports (Box 2)
    - Memoranda and drafts, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
    - Memorandum responding to Arthur Vandenberg, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - Opening remarks, 1944 (Box 2)
    - Papers re Dumbarton Oaks, San Francisco, and London conferences, undated (Box 2)
    - Reactions to Dumbarton Oaks proposals, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - United Nations charter, drafts (Box 3)
      - Early, 1943 (Box 3)
      - Revised, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Institut Universitaire de Hautes Études Internationales, Geneva, Switzerland, 1927, 1951, 1958-1961, 1969 (Box 3)
  - League of Nations (Box 3)
    - Contracts for temporary engagement, 1929-1930 (Box 3)
    - New York World's Fair, Pavilion (Box 3)
      - Addresses and publications, 1939 (Box 3)
      - Building arrangements, 1939 (Box 3)
        - Contracts, (2 folders) (Box 3)
        - Correspondence, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Cables and telegrams, 1939-1941 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
        - General, 1939-1941 (Box 3)
        - Personal, 1939-1940, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Exhibits, 1939, undated (Box 3)
      - Insurance in New York, 1938-1940, including correspondence with Paul Manship regarding damage to his sculpture, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Shipping papers, 1939, (1 folder) (Box 3, Box 4)
    - "World peace procedure," pamphlet by Arthur Sweetser, circa 1929 (Box 4)
  - Personal, including photographs, 1945, 1956, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs, official, undated (Box 4)
  - Preparatory Commission of the United Nations, London, England (Box 4)
    - Handbooks, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and memoranda, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Transfer of League of Nations and its assets to the United Nations (Box 4)
      - Committee reports, agenda, correspondence, 1945-1946, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Committee reports, annotated with Gerig's letters written on verso to Mary Gerig and children, 1945 (Box 4)
      - League of Nations Supervisory Commission, reports, 1944-1946 (Box 4)
      - Telegrams and airgrams, 1946 (Box 4)
  - State Department (Box 4)
    - Africa (Box 4)
      - Cameroon ambassadorial appointment, 1959 (Box 4)
      - Cameroon and Togo, independence celebrations, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      - Informal Conference on Africa South of the Sahara, 1955 (Box 4)
      - Publications, 1956-1959 (Box 4)
    - Colonial policy (Box 4)
      - Memoranda and correspondence, including Alger Hiss letter of 1945 on Yalta Conference 1944-1955, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1947, 1955-1960, 1966-1967, undated (Box 4)
    - Dependent Area Affairs (Box 4)
      - Foreign Service dispatches received, 1955, 1960 (Box 4)
      - Reports, speeches, publications, 1943-1959 (Box 4)
    - Division of International Security and Organization, Office of Special Political Affairs (Box 5)
      - Draft reports regarding the new international organization, 1943-1944 (Box 5)
      - Reports, memoranda, and letters by Quincy Wright regarding international organizations and/or territories, 1943-1944, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Personnel files (Box 5)
      - Appointments (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous appointments and travel orders, 1942-1947 (Box 5)
        - United Nations Trusteeship Council, including letters from Harry S. Truman and Dwight D. Eisenhower 1947, 1952-1953 (Box 5)
      - Awards (Box 5)
        - Certificates, 1949-1954 (Box 5)
        - Superior service, including photograph, 1960 (Box 5)
      - Efficiency/performance ratings, 1943-1959 (Box 5)
      - Personnel actions, notifications, and press releases, 1942-1961 (Box 5)
    - Stevenson, Adlai E., on foreign policy, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - Sweetser, Arthur and Ruth, death of, letters to Gerig, tributes, and obituaries, 1968-1969 (Box 5)
  - United Nations (Box 5)
    - Colonialism, territories, race relations, 1951-1955, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Handbook, first session, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Trusteeship Council (Box 5)
      - Poem, undated (Box 5)
      - Press releases of statements by Gerig, 1956 (Box 5)
      - Verbatim records, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
      - Visiting Mission to Trust Territories in West Africa (1958) chaired by Gerig, correspondence and printed matter, 1949, 1958-1959, undated (Box 6)
    - Trusteeship questions, 1944-1946, undated (Box 6)
  - United Nations Conference on International Organization, San Francisco, Calif. (Box 6)
    - Comments and proposed amendments concerning the Dumbarton Oaks proposals, notebook, 1945, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Discussions re article five of Trusteeship Chapter, 1945, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - General Assembly right to discuss, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Reports on conference developments, 1945 (Box 6)
- Classified (Box CL 1)
  - Subject file (Box CL 1)
    - Dumbarton Oaks Conference, Washington, D.C. (Box CL 1)
      - Conversations, minutes, and documents, 1944 (Box CL 1)
        - Miscellaneous (Container 2) (Box CL 1)
        - Notebook (Container 2), (3 folders) (Box CL 1)
      - Formulation Group, 1944 (Box CL 1)
        - Drafts and proposals (Container 2), (2 folders) (Box CL 1)
        - Memoranda and reports (Container 2) (Box CL 1)
      - Memoranda and drafts, 1942-1943 (Container 2) (Box CL 1)
      - Papers re Dumbarton Oaks, San Francisco, and London conferences, undated (Container 2) (Box CL 1)
      - Reactions to Dumbarton Oaks proposals, undated (Container 2) (Box CL 1)
      - United Nations charter, drafts (Box CL 1)
        - Early, 1943 (Container 3) (Box CL 1)
        - Revised, 1943-1944 (Container 3) (Box CL 1)
    - Preparatory Commission of the United Nations, London, England (Box CL 1)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence and memoranda, 1945 (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
        - Transfer of League of Nations and its assets to the United Nations (Box CL 1)
          - Committee reports, agenda, correspondence, 1946 (folder 2) (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
          - Telegrams and airgrams, 1946 (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
    - State Department (Box CL 1)
      - Africa (Box CL 1)
        - Cameroon and Togo, independence celebrations, 1959-1960 (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
      - Colonial policy (Box CL 1)